Guide to the Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Civil War letters, 1861-1865.
Rudin, Gail and Stephen collection of Civil War letters
- Series I. Letters from various authors
  - Writer: Unknown Soldier - Job Writer's location: Triana, AL Writer's Military Unit: Unknown Addressee: Flora, 7/27/1864 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Refers to "I don't have any inclination whatever of dying" - Talks about "What a fine thing letter writing is" - Mentions his loving attachment to Flora.
  - Writer: Nason B. Will Writer's location: Camp 12th VA, Sussex County, VA Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 12th Virginia Cavalry Addressee: Cousin, 7/27/1864 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Women can fight with broomsticks, flat irons, butcher knives, etc.
  - Writer: George B. Noyes Writer's location: Deep Bottom, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 11th Maine Infantry Addressee: Friend Emery, 7/29/1864 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    The regiment that never runs. "Honor lies on the field and disgrace in the gutter"
  - Writer: Joseph Henry Pierce Writer's location: Before Petersburg Writer's Military Unit: Union, 36th Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Friend, 8/2/1864 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Many of the officers were known to be drunk at the Battle of Crater.
  - Writer: Pvt. Ezra P. Prentice Writer's location: Camp near Petersburg Writer's Military Unit: Union, 5th New York Veteran Volunteers Infantry Addressee: Mother, 8/10/1864 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Life on the picket lines-Trading with the Rebels.
  - Writer: Parris M Lauw Writer's location: Berryville, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 18th Connecticut Infantry Addressee: Wife, 8/19/1864 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Pertaining to the guerrillas operating in the area and tactics against them.
  - Writer: Ensign J. Louis Harris Writer's location: Off Fort Morgan, Mobile Bay Writer's Military Unit: Union, U.S.S. Chickasaw Addressee: Dear Emmie, 8/20/1864 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Fighting on board the ironclad "Chickasaw".
  - Writer: F. H. Bond Writer's location: Fort Federal Hill Baltimore, MD Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Mother, 9/2/1864 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    John Brown-Rebel prisoners-Other war content.
  - Writer: Asst Surgeon C. James Terrell Writer's location: East View? Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Unknown Addressee: General William Taliaferro, 9/23/1864 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Prays for victory and the relief of POWs - Mentions many taking the oath of allegiance to the U.S.
  - Writer: Edward H. Daugherty Writer's location: Pine Bluff, AR Writer's Military Unit: Union, 28th Wisconsin Addressee: Brother, 10/5/1864 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Fighting rebels in Arkansas and hanging a Confederate spy.
  - Writer: Matthew McCann Writer's location: Camp before Petersburg Writer's Military Unit: Union, 132nd Regiment Addressee: Wife and Child, 10/9/1864 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Fraternization - Pickets negotiate a cease fire at the front.
  - Writer: N. Palmer Writer's location: Martinsburg, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Parents, 10/9/1864 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Description of camp life prior to battle.
    Number of pages: 3. Illustrated.
  - Writer: "ALR" Writer's location: Fort Hayes, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Brother, 10/18/1864 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Patriotic letter - "In order to preserve this union unsullied and untarnished, slavery must become extinct"
  - Writer: Robert Taylor Writer's location: Camp Casey Washington DC Writer's Military Unit: Union, 45th Pennsylvania Regiment Co. B Addressee: Miss Rachel Ziza, 10/26/1864 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Love Letter comments, see letter below from 10/27/1864 - 1. Seems that Haws wrote the letter for Taylor. 2. Both letters seem to be written in the same hand. 3. Both women live in Yelaington, Davis County, KY. 4. Both men are in the 45th PA Regiment. 5. Poetry is the same in both letters.
  - Writer: Thorton Haws Writer's location: Camp Casey Washington DC Writer's Military Unit: Union, 45th Pennsylvania Regiment Co. B Addressee: Miss Pegga Taylor, 10/27/1864 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Love Letter comments, see letter above from 10/26/1864 - 1. Seems that Haws wrote the letter for Taylor. 2. Both letters seem to be written in the same hand. 3. Both women live in Yelaington, Davis County, KY. 4. Both men are in the 45th PA Regiment. 5. Poetry is the same in both letters.
  - Writer: Pvt. James E. Russell Writer's location: Point Lookout, MD Writer's Military Unit: Union, 5th Massachusetts Cavalry Addressee: Friend Mr. Okson, 11/13/1864 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Colored cavalryman warns the rebels that the black Yankees are coming.
  - Writer: Edward Minnie (?) Writer's location: Before Petersburg, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Miss. Mary Marsh, 12/18/1864 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Trading sugar and coffee for tobacco - also trading hats for rebel caps.
  - Writer: 2nd Lt. Charles W. Smith Writer's location: Near Petersbury, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 1st Connecticut Artillery Addressee: Miss Emma Leach, 1/21/1865 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Yankee deserts to the rebels.
    Number of pages: 3 1/2 and envelope.
  - Writer: Capt. S. Boyer Davis Writer's location: Johnson's Island, OH Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Unknown Addressee: My Dear Friends, 2/15/1865 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    POW letter written the night before Davis was to be hanged as a spy.
  - Writer: Pvt. E.A. Klipstein Writer's location: Camp 8th VA Regiment Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 8th Virginia Infantry Addressee: Son James, 2/23/1865 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Goose shoot between Yankee and Confederate soldiers.
  - Writer: James Henderson Writer's location: Camp 67th, OH Writer's Military Unit: Union, 67th Ohio Infantry Addressee: Brother and Sister, 3/2/1865 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Exchange papers with rebels - Rebels keep constant firing at night to prevent desertions but they still occur.
  - Writer: William H. Green Writer's location: Nashville, TN Writer's Military Unit: Union, 45th New York Volunteers Addressee: Father and Mother, 3/4/1865 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Tenessee women spit tobacco and smoke cigars - 14 year old deserter.
  - Writer: H.D. Burr Writer's location: On the Weldon Road Writer's Military Unit: Union, 2nd Connecticut Artillery Addressee: Sister, 3/7/1865 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    "What an ocean of blood it has taken to wipe out the stain of slavery"
  - Writer: Pvt. Charles B. Church Writer's location: Camp near Petersburg, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 122nd Ohio Infantry Addressee: Parents, 3/17/1865 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Description of an execution.
  - Writer: Samuel L. Graham Writer's location: Aunt Fanny Daniel's House Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 34th Virginia Infantry Addressee: Cousins, 4/8/1865 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Evacuation and fall of Richmond.
  - Writer: Charles L. Fales Writer's location: Near Clover Hill (Appomattox 30 miles from Lynchburg, VA) Writer's Military Unit: Union, 11th Massachusetts. Volunteers Addressee: Sister, 4/10/1865 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Lee's surrender.
  - Writer: Col. William McArthur Writer's location: Near Appomattox Courthouse in the field, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 8th Maine Volunteers Addressee: Father, 4/13/1865 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Number of pages: 3 1/2
  - Writer: Corp. Patrick Murphy Writer's location: Camp near Burksville, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Uncle and Aunt, 4/19/1865 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Lee's Surrender and Lincoln's Assassination.
  - Writer: Capt. Samuel C. Pierce Writer's location: Suffolk, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 3rd New York Cavalry Addressee: Dearest Ellen, 4/22/1865 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Lincoln's Assassination.
  - Writer: Corp. Arthur M. Stone Writer's location: Richmond, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 34th Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Mother, 4/29/1865 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Surrender of Johnston - Assassination of Lincoln - Appomattox captured flags sent to Washington, DC.
  - Writer: L.A. Jobe Writer's location: Gainsville, AL Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 9th Mississippi Cavalry Addressee: Dearest Kate, 5/5/1865 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Surrender of General Canby and General Johnston.
  - Writer: Col. William McArthur Writer's location: Near Richmond, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 8th Maine Volunteers Addressee: Father, 5/5/1865 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    War's End.
  - Writer: John Allen Writer's location: Hoffman House, NY Writer's Military Unit: N/A, Civilian Addressee: Nephew, 5/12/1865 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    "What an eventful month has been the last in the history of the nation" - mentions surrender of Lee and assassination of Lincoln.
  - Writer: Thomas J. Moore Writer's location: U.S. Military Prison Johnson's Island, OH Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Unknown Addressee: Cousin, 5/23/1865 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Confederate prisoner hates to take The Oath of Allegiance.
  - Writer: Pvt. Charles W. Wall Writer's location: Washington, DC Writer's Military Unit: Union, New York Volunteers Addressee: Capt. William Morgan, 6/5/1865 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Requests leniency for having insulted the captain while drunk.
    Number of pages: 2 1/2
  - Writer: Frank Writer's location: Brooklyn, NY Writer's Military Unit: N/A, Probably a Civilian Addressee: Mrs. Morehouse, 6/9/1865 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    "If anyone has wrongs to correct, the ballot box is the place to do it and not the battlefield"
- Series II. Letters from Dr. William Harrison Githens
  Dr. Githens wrote most of these letters while serving as a surgeon with the 78th Regiment, Illinois Volunteers, 2nd Brigade, 2nd Division 14th Army Corps, and the U.S. General Hospital Division No. 10.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Camp near Hamburg, TN Addressee: Wife, 4/23/1862 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    "Still in all this beautiful land is desolation -the desolation of war." "Our boys seem determined - and most of them are anxious to fight."
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Philadelphia, PA Addressee: Wife, 11/28/1862 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Studying medicine in Phil.-Tours the city during Thanksgiving (Letter is incomplete).
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Bridgeport, AL Addressee: Wife, 9/11/1863 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Describes crossing the mountains on a hard seven mile march with ambulances and twelve hundred teams in the ambulance train.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Field hospital three miles north of Chattanooga, TN Addressee: Wife, 9/30/1863 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Terrible battle on Sunday-"we had 90 ambulances and about 40 wagons loaded-estimated at 700 wounded some of them very badly." "Sixty miles over the mountains"..."six days going and coming"-"thousands of wounded here in tents"..."our boys have proved themselves brave and noble soldiers".
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Chattanooga, TN Addressee: Wife, 11/20/1863 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    "Deserters still come in large numbers than ever. They say there is no use in fighting us any longer that the country is alive with "Yanks"..."It requires a hard struggle to decide between one's family and his country in danger"..."the hardships that may follow are almost too much to be borne. Yet in after years those who live to see the end will look back with pride" - Discusses his finances.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Camp near Chattanooga, TN Addressee: Wife, 12/19/1863 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Back from almost a month long march - Describes the conditions on their return. "Our poor boys were nearly naked-dirty and barefooted". Discusses a possible leave of absence. Shows concern for his wife's pregnancy (confinement). Reviews his finances. "I will have the proud satisfaction of having done my duty for my country."
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hospital, Chattanooga, TN Addressee: Wife, 12/31/1863 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Wife is about to give birth and Githens is anxious to know the result-Talks about a Surgeon's position and the possibility of going home-Mentions a sudden storm and very cold weather-Discusses use of churches and fine residences for hospitals, officer headquarters and for defenses - "This country will bear the devastating marks of war for many a year".
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Near Chattanooga, TN Addressee: Louise (Daughter), Late 1863 ? (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Reminds her of the importance of writing and spelling, as well as music - Wants her to be a good scholar -""Jack" (a black boy) has just come with his book wrong end up to ask me what some little letters spell"..."He seems pretty sharp"..."some of the Black Boys learn to read in a few weeks"... "if they only had teachers some of them would make good scholars"... "you wish for me to come home - how will the poor wounded boys get along - they must be taken care of"..."some of the poor fellows still lay here in the field Hospitals - poor and pale" - Talks about family affairs. Signed "Father"
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: U.S. General Hospital, Chattanooga, TN Addressee: Wife, 1/20/1864 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Wife has given birth to a boy-Mentions children and family-Discusses a leave of absence disapproved-Conditions at camp are much improved-Mentions Battle of Chickamauga and Mission Ridge-Many people are returning, bands are playng as civilization returns.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: U.S. General Hopsital, Chattanooga, TN Addressee: Wife, 1/24/1864 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Talks of church services, the singing, the sermon-Anxious to get home on leave of absence-Thinks, for the children, "I could commence with new energies" and "make a name for myself that they would be proud of". Closes by saying "I have seen enough of battles and war-and have satisfied myself that I am not a coward-but a man is a fool to want to see more than one battle". (See also 9/18/64).
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Brigade hospital, near Rossville, GA Addressee: Wife, 2/10/1864 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    He is very homesick and has received no letters- But "when I think how much is needed and how much willing hands may do, I feel that there is no way but to gather fresh courage and try a while longer" - Talks about deserters - "The desolation and sorrow that they have caused will be a stain on them as long as they live"..."poor deluded mortals they know not what they did".
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Headquarters, near Rossville, GA Addressee: Wife, 4/29/1864 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    May at any moment get marching orders and is sending most of his clothing to the rear-Went out to the battlefields to take up the dead for burial in the new U.S. Cemetery in Chattanooga-"we were glad to have a chance to put the poor fellows where they can rest in peace-we must not think defeat after having gained so much". Also talks about their financial position.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Camp, in the woods in the rail road about five miles from Marietta, GA Addressee: Wife, 6/15/1864 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Discusses a potential battle for Marietta and is very positive about their military position-Mentions the Southern corn diet-Wishes he could be home for the 4th of July-Describes the band music that cheers the troops-Discusses the rebel deserters who are lied to by their officers and keep coming every day-"the poor deluded folks keep on fighting and sacrificing thousands of lives on both sides" - Army has complete confidence in General Sherman and "we'll go wherever he tells them".
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Camp, three or four miles southwest of Marietta, GA Addressee: Wife, 6/26/1864 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Writes about Church - "today being a beautiful Sabbath as calm and quiet as though no such thing as war existed" - Wishes he was home - Mentions General Sherman's strategy of "running around their (Rebel) ends" - Discusses his pay and his finances.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hospital, Chattahoochee River, GA Addressee: Wife, 7/9/1864 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Mentions "there has been but little fighting for a few days...we have a very large force across the river and the prospect is very fair that we will be in Atlanta before long" - Writes "ours and the Rebel picket lines are close together...will all have some wonderful old soldier stories to tell if we get home".
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hospital, Chattahoochie River, Trinings (?) Station, GA Addressee: Daughter, 7/12/1864 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Writes "Don't think how anxious we soldiers are to get letters on anything from home - reminding us of comfort and plenty-and the quiet times of peace" - Asks that his daughter attend diligently to her studies - Talks about his son Willie - Hopes Ma will have enough money to raise chickens and two or three pigs - Mentions that the sick and wounded get plenty to eat and are well cared for.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hospital, 4 Miles from the Chattahoochee on the road to Atlanta, GA Addressee: Wife, 7/22/1864 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    "Atlanta is ours" - "We had quite a number wounded in the Division and a good many sick"..." dressing wounded before sunrise-and worked til late in the day before ambulances were sent - then we loaded and sent away load after load until late in the night"..."I don't doubt that there is more rejoicing at home than here" - "the soldier soon becomes indifferent to all joys and sorrows" - Describes John McGovern's roadside grave - "How we long for the slaughter to stop"
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hospital, 5 or 6 miles from Atlanta, GA Addressee: Wife, 7/26/1864 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Mentions that he was mistaken; Atlanta has not been taken but their forces occupy strong positions-Writes about possible new hospital locations-Conditions are good except for thousands of flies - "They are into everything-we hardly bother to skim them out of our coffee or soup." Talks about how hard it is to replace clothing - "Things are so enormously high that I can hardly afford them" (Letter is incomplete)
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hospital, 5 miles S.W. Atlanta, GA Addressee: Wife, 8/22/1864 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Talks about the children, their finances, improvements on the house - He needs clothes -"I am the shabbiest dressed Medical Officer here" - Comments on the campaign "our Commander is not very keen to take Atlanta just at present" - Discusses in graphic terms the treatment of battle wounds.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hospital, Atlanta, GA Addressee: Wife, 9/8/1864 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Mentions improvements to the house-His division is going to garrison Atlanta-He is in charge of the Amputated Ward and the worst cases and gets a great many compliments from the soldiers- Gen'l Sherman has issued orders to remove the rebel civilians-"it seems cruel almost to require families to leave their homes and go, they know not where" - Discusses distinctions in rank -Talks about a future medical practice and that he will no longer accept any position in the Army.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Dept. Cumberland Medical College Atlanta, GA Addressee: Wife, 9/15/1864 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Mentions slowly entering Atlanta-Using bales of cotton for beds-"I suppose there was a good deal of rejoicing all through the North at our success-but we took it very cooly-one thing made it different, our sad losses-and the care of the wounded". Describes the environment, train whistles, engine bells, various bands, etc. - "quite a contrast to laying out in the woods for months and being treated to ten inch shells for music" - Balance of letter is about getting paid and his finances; also about the surgical skills he has developed.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Medical College, Atlanta, GA Addressee: Wife, 9/18/1864 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Discusses a church service - Only thing missing is the female voice - Soldiers on guard at the door - Soldiers are taking "a resting spell" - Working day and night to build comfortable quarters - Mentions how homes are destroyed to get wood and brick.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Officers' Hospital, 24th and Chestnut St. Philadelphia, PA Addressee: Wife, 2/18/1865 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    "I feel like getting well rapidly-gaining strength quite fast"..."I expect it will be several days yet before I am in condition to travel". Talks about getting home and his plans for the future - "I shall count the hours until I am free once more yet I would much prefer to see the war ended first-You know I would get a little credit for the long years of hardship already endured if I should come home a few months before the rest did. Still that would matter very little if my own conscience was satisfied"
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Camp, Holly Springs, NC Addressee: Wife, 4/27/1865 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    "This cruel war is over at last and we are to start for home" - Talks about travel arrangements to get home - Has ordered newspapers containing information about Lincoln's murder - Closes letter by saying "when orders are read that all the rebel armies have surrendered and that we are to go home, then the woods ring - old hats go up into the air and every kind of noisy demonstration is resorted to"
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Headquarters, near Fort Slemmer, Washington, DC Addressee: Daughter, 6/2/1865 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    He is on his way home hopefully looking forward to a 4th of July welcome celebration - "all these days of toil are over and I hope forever - still we do not regret what we have endured when we think how much good it has done"
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Headquarters, camp, near Fort Slemmer, Washington, DC Addressee: Wife, 6/6/1865 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Disappointed that he has been detained so long and is going through such tedious paperwork - "I shall be so glad when I am once more free - when I can call myself and my time my own"..."I am more impatient at a week's delay than I used to be at a month"..."it seems that I have grown so accustomed to excitement and danger that the dull monotony of home life will soon tire - I hope not - for I used to love home as well as anyone"
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Hamilton, IL Addressee: Sarah (Githen's grand - daughter), 4/8/1901 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Congratulates his granddaughter on the fact that she is about to receive her teacher's credentials - Talks about the weather and the and the local bird population - Mentions family affairs - Signed "Gramps"
  - Writer: The Carthage Republican Writer's location: Carthage, IL, 7/13/1904 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    The Carthage Republican - Githens' Obituary
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Unknown Addressee: Mr. President, No date (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Discusses horticulture and gardening.
    Number of pages: 8 page photocopy
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Nashiville, Tennessee and Macon City, Missouri Addressee: Wife, 1/1861-9/1861 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Three letters, two are just dealer description not the actual letter, all are copies. Discuss churches in Nashville TN, illness of soldiers, living conditions, Battle of Platt City, MO.
    Number of pages: 5 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 2/1862-1862 (Box 4, Folder 31)